What's up, Dolph fans? Welcome back into
Dolphins HQ. For today's episode, we're
jumping right into the film room to
introduce you to new Dolphins
quarterback Malik Willis. I have six
plays. So, stay with me here talking
about all the things he brings to this
Dolphins quarterback room. First, a
couple of plays playing in structure,
reading the defense, and making really
good throws down the field. This is a
40-yard completion to Romeo Dobs up the
sideline right in the bucket there. The
exceiver to the boundary. Drop that
thing in there, make some rain on the
throw, and move the change for a big
completion. Go back to the beginning of
the play right here though. Watch this
hard count right here. And the safety
rotation. We're going to walk this
safety down. He's going to peek that.
Here comes a little hard count. Nope.
We're not going to snap that thing. But
we know he's coming downhill. So now we
know that we have one-on-one coverage to
the boundary and we're going to go ahead
and make that throw because we have the
identification of the coverage pre- snap
and the skills to put the ball on the
money post snap. Big time play there
from Malik Willis to kick off this game
against the Ravens. Here's the end zone
copy one more time. Peak that safety.
Get your defense identified. Take the
snap. throw a shot, make some rain, put
it in the bucket. Big completion right
there. Let's go to this next play right
here. Another really good deep throw
from Malik Willis. We're gonna have a
four verts concept right here against
what becomes a middle of the field open
with split safeties. And what we're
going to do is read this safety's hips.
We're going to open to the outside and
widen. He's going to widen as well. And
it creates the access of the seam throw
right here to Christian Watson for a
39yd touchdown. One hitch timing off the
top of the drop. Rip that thing up the
seam. hit it in stride and it goes in
for six. So, I want you to watch the way
he hits top of the drop right here and
fires this thing down the field. Quite
frankly, that's all the analysis you
really need on this play. The tape kind
of speaks for itself right here. But, I
do want to show you one thing about his
throwing mechanics right here. How
compact his motion is and just how
smooth and efficient the mechanics are
in general. So, watch this the throw
here from the end zone copy. But just
watch the way everything is so compact.
And I want you to watch this right hip.
The way it fires towards the target and
follows his right shoulder down the pipe
right there. That is how you coach it in
terms of mechanics and playing tight to
your mechanical alignment, your
proficiency to make an accurate throw up
the field down the seam for a big
touchdown. How about when it breaks down
and we have to get outside of the
structure here a little bit. Keep the
eyes up, reset your your body, move
again, find new space in the pocket, and
throw that thing down the field with a
crazy arm angle. drop that thing like a
pitcher in baseball down around the hip
and fire on the money amid all the
pressure here that he's going to face on
this drop back. Go ahead and go to the
end zone copy right here. Watch the
pressure he gets. Kind of feel it out.
Move to some space right there. Oh, that
escape hatch is taken away. Move back
again. There's the opener. And then drop
that arm down below the shoulder right
there and fire it for a completion. And
a big run after catch for another first
down here for the Packers. So, some off
structure, some in structure. How about
some designed run game right here? a
zone read touchdown around the corner
for 22 yards and a touchdown to the
pylon. I want you to watch these outside
defenders converge on the inside give
here on a little zone read concept. I'll
go ahead and show you this play in full
right here as he takes it around the
corner and see you later. We're in for a
touchdown. 22 yards. A big game-breaking
play with the legs right there from
Malik Willis. Right here, watch the
helmet. He's going to be his helmet
shows you everything you need to see
about the way he sees the defense and
reads things out. We're here. We're
going to peak these backside contained
defenders. And for you Dolphins fans
that have watched Devon Aan hit
explosive runs time and time again. Now
you have this element in your offense
with this quarterback where these
backside defenders have to stay home.
They have to keep contained. Otherwise,
this is going to happen to you cuz
watch, he's reading this thing out right
here. Put the ball in the belly of the
back. Eyes are on that backside
defender. They're crashing. So, we're
going to keep it and run right around
the corner. 22 yards for six and another
Packers touchdown right there. Let's go
back to some more creativity and off
structure plays here from the new
Dolphins quarterback. This one is going
to be a pretty simple get out right away
and throw the ball down the field and
just kind of watch the traits here on
the move. Throw this ball about 30 yards
down the field on the money while moving
out to the right. Pretty impressive
stuff here from your new quarterback for
another big completion. He's going to
feel the pressure immediately. Get out
of it and create and buy some time.
Sometimes plays don't work. You see the
pressure in the A gap right there
because they're going to walk up and
show six in pressure right here. We've
got six to protect it, but we're going
to actually bust in the A gap right here
as this this gap kind of gets exposed.
Running back steps over to pick it up,
but we just want to get out and kind of
create some more space to buy some more
time in the concept. He's going to
threaten this flat route. They're going
to drive down, throw it up over the top
for a big completion once again on the
move outside of the structure. And this
might be my favorite one of all of them
because of all the things we just talked
about kind of all come into play on this
particular clip. We're going to try to
throw the middle of the field right here
on a crossing route, a dig route. But
you're going to get a quadrant of Ravens
defenders that take that away. But what
I want you to watch is the way Malik
Willis's eyes stay down the field. And
he processes information after the fact
while he's dealing with pressure in the
pocket. Now, that's not pressure. That's
a clean pocket. He wants to step up and
rip this thing from that clean pocket.
He's not bailing on the clean pocket,
but it's just not there. So, now we're
going to have to create because the pass
concept is not open. So this kind of
deep mesh concept opens up more as he
buys more time. And a good job by Watson
to continue to move here into the
pattern and just get outside the
structure of the play. And just watch
the way Malik can kind of move around
the pocket and fire this thing off
platform. So the the sideline copy here
shows you the process and how he wants
to play on time in rhythm. It's not
there. The option for that is not there.
So now we have to create which he does
and then finds him for a big gain down
the field. Let's go ahead and watch the
pocket work here from Malik Willis from
the end zone copy. show you the top of
the drop where he wants to throw this
thing against a three-man rush into that
kind of quadrant of Ravens defenders,
but it's not there. So, reset, move
again, reset once again. Oh, there's
pressure. We'll get out of that. Move to
the left and fire this thing with a
dropped arm angle off one foot. It's
really impressive the physical traits
that he offers. So, Malik Willis, your
new Miami Dolphins quarterback, run game
in structure, outside of structure. A
little bit of everything on the tape for
him against for the Packers last year,
now in Miami.
What's up, Dolph fans? Welcome back to
Dolphins HQ. My guest today for the
second time ever, first time this year.
You know who he is, Kenneth Grant.
Kenny, what's up, man?
>> What's going on? How you doing?
>> I'm doing pretty good. I like having
these interviews where it's like a year
apart because I can ask you what has
life been like for the last year.
Obviously, I've watched you play a bunch
of football, but how has life changed
for you in the last year? Whether it's
on the field, off the field, just what
has the first year of being a pro, being
in South Florida? What's that been like
for you? It it's been pretty good in
South Florida to be honest. You know,
they got all the resources here. You
know, even in the facility on the field,
you know, great resources here, great
people here. So, just continuing to
improve on things like that. But off the
field, you know, trying to get my life
together, getting new houses and things
like that, getting that stuff in order.
>> What do you get into in your free time?
You you going out to some restaurants?
You going fishing? Like, what's a what's
a free day for Kenneth Grant look like?
>> Yeah, I like to get outdoors to be
honest. like uh I think it was like two
weeks ago me and uh Matt Butler, one of
the linemen, we went uh hog hunting down
here. It was about an hour and a half
away. So we went hog hunting. We took it
to the butcher house, cut it up and
stuff. So really
>> Yeah, that's pretty cool.
>> No Zack Seer involvement in that.
>> That's like his world, man.
>> I know. He's uh he's actually uh the guy
that put us on to to the guy. So
>> that doesn't surprise me. Yeah,
>> probably up his neck of the woods. I
know him and his him and his family and
Sebring have like a whole like a whole
Glades excursion thing. You interested
in doing stuff like that? going to chase
some alligators and stuff.
>> Uh yeah, that that'll be pretty cool.
One of my my next tasks going deep sea
fishing or alligator hunting. So, you
know,
>> so you mentioned uh you know all the
resources here that we have with the
team and everything. What does a day in
the life of your off seasonason look
like in terms of the workout and the way
you prepare for the next season? What
does it look like when you come to the
building every day and kind of get ready
for next year?
>> Yeah, so I try to take care of my things
really early in the morning. You know, I
get here around like 8 o'clock in the
sauna hot tub and things like that. get
warmed up for the nine o'clock uh run
and lift. So do that, do the nine
o'clock run and lift and then probably
after that uh get back in the sauna and
things like that for about like an hour,
hour and a half and then the rest of the
day is just really stretch and you know
eating the right things, you know,
because we have a lot of free time. So I
mean eating can be a hassle, but you
know you got to know how to control it
and and eat really good things, which
another thing John Par and Adriana,
they've been really good with helping me
doing things like that. So, it's been
been amazing.
>> There's a lot of really good options
down there. A lot of they got to go to
the grilled chicken and the salad bar,
man. Try to keep your
>> It's a mind game for sure down there.
>> Um, so, you know, in the in the
offseason, I'm sure you're trying to
like bulk a little more in terms of the
weights, right? Like it's a different
lift than what it is during the season.
I remember reading you on the Bruce
Feldman's Freaks list. Are you aware of
what that is? Like the college
prospects, like the guys that do the
most weights and stuff like that.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I've been mentioning that.
>> Are you uh like what do you what are we
talking these days? is like what are
some of the numbers on on some of these
these lifts?
>> We don't really do numbers, you know, we
do a lot of uh a lot of volume sets. So,
you know, sets of 10, sets of 12. Um
we're kind of transitioning right now
probably this week to getting into heavy
weeks, heavier weights.
>> Yeah, pretty impressive stuff. And that
was kind of what I wanted to talk to you
about was just what that first year did
to inform you for your second year.
whether it's technique like your hand
placement, right? Trying to read keys in
a block or whether it's your nutrition
plan or how you lift weights, like what
are some of the biggest lessons you took
from your rookie season that you're
excited to apply here in year two?
>> To be honest, one of the very re the
very most recent reasons that you know I
I come come here and train every day is
because every day here is going to be a
work day. Like it you either come here,
give your 100% or don't come at all.
That's kind of the life in the NFL to to
be honest. So, I mean that that's one of
the big reasons uh you know that big
lessons that I learned this last year
was you know you got to bring your all
every day
>> every single day especially with Austin
Clark right when he's coaching you. How
excited are you to have him back for
year two here?
>> I'm really excited. You know, really
comfortable with him. You know, he's a
very personal guy off the field, but on
the field, you know, he he gets in in
his business. So, I mean, I'm very
excited to take it to another notch and
I don't know he could take me there. So,
one thing we talked about when we had
you on right after the draft was just
some of the the finer points of playing
into your defensive line and I was
curious just kind of following up that
question whether it's like hand
placement, reading keys, like whether
you're playing different positions. What
did you kind of take away from all the
stuff that you I guess absorbed as a
rookie playing all those spots and kind
of having things click for you? Is it
fair to say that things kind of clicked
into place for you right around like
Octoberish when your play kind of
started going up? What was that that
kind of made that click and what are
some of the things that you noticed that
are just a little bit different at this
level? Yeah, it was really just slowing
my mind down, getting back to my
fundamentals and techniques because, you
know, in the NFL w with with all of
that, if you don't have your fundamental
techniques and you try to do all this
fancy stuff, you can get into big
trouble. So, you know, I started off,
you know, trying to do too much at at
the start. So, you know, Coach Clark uh
got me back to doing that, getting me
back to my fundamentals and techniques.
So, um I think that's that's what took
my game to to elevate. Yeah, there was I
I watched a bunch of your highlights
before we did this and there was some
plays where it's just quick dispatch,
man. You beat the guys so fast that
there's really no chance. And one of the
things we do here on HQ is try to
educate fans about the game of football
and your position is so unique for that
because I mean like I I played baseball
and like hitting a fast ball is tough,
but when you're trying to like if a a
guard wants to reach you and you have to
like kind of back door him, but maybe he
winds up settling back in front of you
and all of a sudden you have to rush
through him. There's so much that
happens like in a split second, right?
How does how does your mind operate from
the time that you have your hand in the
dirt to when that ball is snapped and
all of a sudden like your plan is being
put into place, but then it has to
adjust? Just take us through like what's
that what that's like for a player to
have to play on the fly like that. If
that makes sense.
>> Yeah, to be honest, you just got to it
it's all with with your eyes. Your eyes
start first. Wherever in defensive
linement world, wherever your eyes are,
that's where your body is going to take
you. So we really try to focus on, you
know, keeping our eyes in the right
place and and then everything falls
after that. Hips, hands, and feet fall
after that because it, you know, we use
an analogy of if you're looking to the
left and you're trying to punch someone
to the right, you're going to miss. So,
you know, we always trying to, you know,
that's our that's our first and foremost
thing is eyes and fundamentals.
>> Yeah. Because there's so many plays
where it's like it looks like you want
to rush half the man and then based on
the set or just the play call, you wind
up going through him and that's a
different rush, right? going through a
guy versus around him.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So everything happens in
>> two two and a half three seconds. So it
it happens really fast. So you got to
have you know your eyes in the right
place and then your hands will also help
you. So you know it's a collective
accumulative of all those things and
fundamentals that you know that you
really need to play in defensive
lineman.
>> So you're one of three guys that got
significant playing time among the
rookie class last year at that position.
Do you guys kind of help motivate and
fuel each other to push your guys push
yourselves to to newer heights?
>> Yeah, most definitely. We we talk uh
almost pretty often, probably every day,
you know, just see checking up on guys,
seeing how they're doing, what they're
doing to, you know, feel their bodies
and things like that. You know, we try
to learn off each other, you know, help
each other out and find different ways
to do different things and challenge
challenge ourselves, you know, during
this offseason.
>> Yeah, I'm glad you got coach Clark back
for that continuity, but we do have a
new coaching staff in general here with
coach Halfley coming in. What have been
your first impressions so far of him and
the new staff?
>> You know, he's a really great dude. you
know, he's very personable and easy to
talk to, to be honest. But, you know,
once we started talking about the our
aspirations and goals for the next
football season, you know, you could
tell it it he changed in the mood. You
know, he's very serious about that. You
know, he I can tell that he he wants to
win a lot and, you know, he he's doing
everything in his power to to get us to
sustain winners.
>> Yeah. I' I've heard a lot about like
mental and physical toughness from him,
right? How do you think that suits your
game and your makeup?
>> I think it suits me pretty good. you
know, just I always consider myself, you
know, very mentally tough. Um, aside
from being physically tough, but, you
know, I I always want to, you know,
sustain that mental toughness.
>> So, you we started this interview
talking a little bit about your time in
South Florida here. I know you just
participated in the DCC. Tell us about
that and kind of your experience in that
and your why behind why it's important
to you.
>> Yeah, that was a great experience to be
honest. It was a lot of people that came
out. You know, it was it was a lot of
random fans. Like we were down riding in
uh we started in uh University of Miami.
There's a lot of people out even like
people that weren't riding there on the
sidewalk, you know, cheering us on. It
was it was a great community event cuz I
I didn't even know it was that big to be
honest.
>> It's a big deal, man. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It was crazy. But, you know, my
why towards that is because uh my
grandparents, you know, they passed away
from cancer. One of my grandpas are he's
still alive, but you know, he he's
battling through that. So that's pretty
much my main reason why.
>> Who did you ride with?
>> Uh I rode with my girlfriend. Okay.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I rode with my girlfriend
and then Joan and his girlfriend. We
rode together. So it was pretty fun.
>> Didn't get a chance to see Patrick Paul.
Patrick had the uh what do you call the
I don't even know the name of them.
>> The meta glasses.
>> Were you on any of his shots at all?
>> Uh yeah, I think I was. We actually
passed uh Ali and Dante Trader. They
were doing the 5K.
>> Uh yeah.
>> The 5K run or walk. But you know, pass
those guys. That was pretty cool. So,
what how many miles did you do this
year?
>> I did 39.
>> You thinking about going up next year?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Me and Coach Clark, we
already talked about we were like,
"Yeah, why not just do the 54?"
>> 54. Okay. You get one of those pedal
assist bikes, though. Maybe you can go
99. Those are those are pretty easy.
>> I I don't think they'll last the battery
power. Kenneth Grant here on the
Dolphins on Dolphins HQ. Appreciate your
time today, man. And uh we'll see you
again soon.
>> Yes, sir.
That will do it here for this episode of
Dolphins HQ from the Baptist Health
Studios. Don't forget to check out the
Drive Time podcast hosted by yours truly
available three days per week wherever
you get your podcast. Subscribe to the
Dolphins YouTube channel for all
offseason content and media
availabilities. We hope to see you back
here very soon.